Guide to the Recordsings of Sunrise Semester Programs RG.7.3.1.1
New York University Archives
Recordings of Sunrise Semester Programs
1958-1982
New York University Archives
New York University
RG.7.3.1.1
85 Linear Feet in 348 upright video containers, 10 record cartons, 4 CD boxes, and 2 manuscript boxes
205 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
202 1_Inch_Video_Reel
146 2_Inch_Videoreel
24 U-matic
8 16mm_film_reels
5 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
1 VHS
The Recordings of Sunrise Semester Programs contain video, audio, and film recordings of NYU course lectures aired as the Sunrise Semester program on WCBS-TV from 1958-1982. Courses covered a wide variety of subjects, including math, sciences, literature, writing, communications, politics, theology, and anthropology.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was donated to NYU in 2008 by CBS. 122 audio recordings were transferred to the University Archives by the Academic Affairs Office in 1982. The accession number associated with this transfer is 82.066. 7 16mm films were transferred to the University Archives by the New York University Department of Classics in 1999. 44 1/4" audio reels were transferred to the University Archives by former psychology professor Lawrence Balter in July 2010. The accession number associated with this transfer is 10.013.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically. Recordings from the same course are grouped together and arranged by episode number wherever possible.
Historical Note
Sunrise Semester was a television series that aired from 1957 to 1982 on WCBS-TV in collaboration with New York University's College of Arts and Science. The series was an early example of distance learning in which NYU faculty members would present accredited courses in a wide range of academic subjects.
Sunrise Semester was broadcast at 6:30am EST and offered two courses a semester, six days a week. Each course consisted of three half-hour lectures per week for approximately fifteen weeks. Repeat radio broadcasts of the entire series were aired at 7:30 pm EST on WNYU-FM (89.1 MHz), a radio station serving New York City.
Course requirements were at the discretion of the NYU professor giving the lecture, but generally included a term paper and final exam. During the semester, students in the NYC metropolitan area could attend any of the optional six two-hour evening discussion groups or arrange individual meetings with the professors. Throughout the series, viewers could take courses for credit at NYU or transfer the credits to participating home institutions. In the height of its popularity, 200 academic institutions across the country offered Sunrise Semester courses for credit.
Beginning with "Comparative Literature from Stendhal to Hemingway" taught by Dr. Floyd Zulli in 1957, Sunrise Semester courses covered a wide variety of subjects including math, sciences, literature, writing, communications, politics, theology, and anthropology. In 1980, NYU attempted to revitalize the program and enlarge its audience, and began offering the ability to earn a Masters in Liberal Studies by taking Sunrise Semester courses. In 1981, NYU also introduced interdisciplinary courses into Sunrise Semester.
Sunrise Semester won four Emmys and two Ohio State Awards between 1958 and 1960, and its viewership continued to grow throughout the 1960s and 1970s. By 1972, the program aired on 85 CBS affiliates with an estimated number of viewers between 1.3 to 2 million. By 1980, it was the longest running educational program in the history of broadcasting. However, the program was terminated by CBS in 1982 due to declining viewership as well as academic and legal concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Access CDs for audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Related Materials
See MC 286, Box 1 for Sunrise Semester Course Bulletins.
See RG 19, Box 47 for the Office of the Dean's administrative files on Sunrise Semester.
See RG 3.0.7, Box 67 for NYU President James McNaughton Hester's 1971 administrative papers regarding Sunrise Semester.
See RG 6.0, Box 25 for NYU President Henry T. Heald and Vice President John Eli Ivey, Jr.'s papers regarding the first two years of Sunrise Semester.
See RG 6.0.7, Box 75 for NYU President Sidney Borowitz's 1972-1976 administrative papers regarding Sunrise Semester.
See RG 7.3.1, Series II for Office of Radio and Television Records associated with Sunrise Semester.
Scope and Contents
The Recordings of Sunrise Semester Programs (1958-1982) contain video, audio, and film recordings of NYU course lectures aired as Sunrise Semester on WCBS-TV. Some courses are represented in only a couple of recordings, while others have more complete runs. The majority of this collection consists of open reel video recordings that were used by CBS Broadcasting, Inc. The collection also includes open reel audio recordings, which were broadcast in evenings on WNYU, and a smaller number of 16mm films and U-matic recordings.
Early Sunrise Semester courses in this collection include "The Tragic Dramas of Greece and Rome" with Professor Lionel Casson (1958), "The Legacy of Greece and Rome" with Professor Richard Haywood (1958), and "Classic Literature" (1958), and a History course on the Middle East with Professor Henry Noss (circa 1959). These were largely captured on 16mm film.
Sunrise Semester in the 1960s is represented through audio and video recordings from about a dozen courses. These courses include "Shakespeare: Complete Plays" with Professor Richard C. Harrier (1960), "Introduction to Ethics" with Professor Sidney Hook (1963), "The Age of Michelangelo" with Professor Kathleen Weil-Garris Brandt (1965), "Have You Read..." with Professor Floyd Zulli (1966), and "Philosophical Analysis" with Professor Kai Nielsen (1966).
The 1970s were the height of Sunrise Semester's popularity, and make up the bulk of this collection. These courses include "Classical Mythology in Literature, Art, and Music" with Professor Philip Mayerson (1971), "Communication, The Invisible Environment" with Professor Neil Postman (1977), "Discipline in the Classroom: Social and Emotional Problems" with Professor Lawrence Balter (1977), and "Drama in Education" with Professor Robert Landy (1979).
Finally, this collection includes many episodes from Sunrise Semester's final courses in 1980, 1981, and 1982. These courses include "Learning to Write / Writing to Learn" with Professor John Mayher (1980), "Women and Men in a Changing Society" with Dr. Marilyn Young and Dr. Ellen Ross (1981), "Radio, Television, and the New Technology" with Professor Dr. L. Theresa Silverman (1981), and four 1982 courses with incomplete titles labeled "AL Labor," "Child," "EJ Seniors," and "TH Ethics."
Course titles are described in full wherever possible, whether derived from the audiovisual containers themselves or from course bulletins and administrative records in the University Archives. Some course codes could not be described in full at the time of processing, and are instead described exactly as they are written on the audiovisual containers (i.e. "EJ Seniors"). Some videos are labeled as either a "Standby" or "Air" copy, which are identical in content but were used for different purposes within the broadcasting studios. Episode numbers are listed in sequential order within each course, and may repeat across courses.
Six boxes containing open reel audio and video recordings could not be located at the time of processing this collection in June 2025. Consequently, some original recordings for the courses "Shakespeare: Complete Plays" with Professor Richard C. Harrier (1960) and "Peoples of Africa" with Assistant Professor Elliot P. Skinner (1960) cannot be served to researchers at this time.
Educational television programs; Distance education.; Lectures.; Video tapes.; Audiotapes.; Television broadcasting -- United States.; Mayerson, Phillip; Balter, Lawrence; Johnson, Jotham; Postman, Neil; Harrier, Richard; CBS/Broadcast Group (New York, N.Y.); Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; Mayher, John; Casson, Lionel, 1914-2009; Noss, Henry; Posner, Kathleen; Nielsen, Kai; Landy, Robert J.; Ross, Ellen.; Young, Marilyn.; Zulli, Floyd, 1922-1980
- Course on the Middle East with Professor Henry Noss, circa 1950s
  - Film (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0380)
  - Film (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0379)
- "The Tragic Dramas of Greece and Rome" with Professor Lionel Casson, June, 1958
  - Film, June 16, 1958 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0382)
  - Episode #43, June 16, 1958 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0383)
  - Film, June 27, 1958 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0384)
- "Classic Literature" -- Episode #43, June 23, 1958 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0377)
- "The Legacy of Greece and Rome" with Professor Richard Haywood -- Film, January 7, 1959 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0381)
- "Shakespeare: Complete Plays" with Professor Richard C. Harrier, October, 1960
  - "Julius Caesar" (Acts II-V), October 1-6, 1960
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0332)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:19, 4:20)
  - "Julius Caesar," "Romeo and Juliet", October 8-13, 1960
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0331)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:21)
  - "Romeo and Juliet: The Character of Juliet"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:22)
  - "Macbeth: Act I"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:23)
  - "Macbeth: Acts I and II"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:24)
  - "Macbeth: Act II"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:25)
  - "Macbeth: Act III"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:26)
  - "Macbeth: Acts III and IV"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:27)
  - "Othello: Acts I and II"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:2)
  - "Othello: Acts II and III"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:1)
  - "Hamlet: Act I"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:3)
  - "Othello: Acts IV and V"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:4)
  - "Hamlet: Act III (part I)"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:5)
  - "Hamlet: Act III (part II)"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:6)
  - "Hamlet: Acts I and II: Plot and Counterplot"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:7)
  - "Hamlet: Act II: Hamlet and the Players"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:7)
  - "King Lear: Acts I and II"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:8)
  - "King Lear: Act I"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:11)
  - "King Lear: Act V: The Meaning of the Play"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:12)
  - "Antony and Cleopatra: Act I"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:12)
  - "King Lear: Acts III and IV: The Contrasting Tragedies of Gloucester and Lear"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:13)
  - "King Lear (Unspecified) (Partial)"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:14)
  - "Theory of Tragedy and Shakespearean Tragedy"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:15)
  - "Antony and Cleopatra: Acts III and IV"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:16)
  - "Antony and Cleopatra: Acts IV and V"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:16)
- "Peoples of Africa" with Assistant Professor Elliot P. Skinner, Fall, 1960
  - "The Pasturalists of Africa"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:22)
  - "Complex Political Systems: Part II"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:28)
- "Classical Civilization" with Professor Jotham Johnson -- Episode #56, April 11, 1961 (Box 11, 16mm film reels 7.3.1.1.0378)
- "Introduction to Ethics" with Professor Sidney Hook, September 23, 1963 - January 10, 1964
  - Reel #1, "The Nature and Importance of Ethical Theory," "Types of Moral Judgment," "The Ethics of Power," "The Skeptic's Challenge", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0360)
    - Access CD (Box 14, Cd 2:43)
  - Reel #2, "The Limits of Power," "The Quest for Justice," "Theories of Social Analysis," "Justice as Reward for Merit", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0360)
    - Access CDs (Box 14, Cd 2:44, 2:45, 2:46)
  - Reel #3, "Justice and Human Need," "The Limits of Justice," "The Platonic Theory of Justice," "The Cult of Pleasure," "The Refutation of Egoistic Hedonism", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0358)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:1, 3:2)
  - Reel #5, "The Test of Moral Conduct," "A Critique of Kant," "Human Rights and Duties," "The Ethics of Compassion," "The Limits of Non-Resistance or Passiveness to Evil", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0357)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:3, 3:4, 3:5)
  - Reel #6, "The Role of Authority in Moral Life," "The Authority of Religion," "Religion and the Problem of Evil", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0356)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:6, 3:7, 3:8)
  - Reel #9, "Epicurianism," "Existentialism," "The Life of Reason", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0355)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:9, 3:10)
  - Reel #10, "The Justification of Punishment," "Theories of Punishment," "The Free Will and Free Man," "Determinism and Responsibility," "The Language and Logic of Ethics: Intuitionism", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0354)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:11, 3:12, 3:13, 3:14)
  - Reel #11, "Subjectivism," "The Good Reasons Approach," "The Uses of Life and Death," "John Dewey", undated (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0353)
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0353)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Quarter inch audio reel 3:15)
  - Reel #12, "Conclusion: Further Uses of Life and Death", undated (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0352)
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0352)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:16)
- "The Age of Michelangelo" with Professor Kathleen Weil-Garris Brandt, 1965
  - "An Introduction to The Age of Michelangelo," "The Man and His Art," "Inheritor of a Great Tradition", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0351)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:17, 3:18, 3:19, 3:20)
  - Reel #2, "Birth of the Renaissance in Italy, "New Ideas From Florence," "Earliest Years: His Teachers", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0350)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:21, 3:22, 3:23, 3:24)
  - Reel #3, "Journey of Discovery," "Michelangelo in Rome: The Bacchus and the Pieta," "Two Great Battle Frescoes", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0349)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:25, 3:26, 3:27, 3:28, 3:29)
  - Reel #5, "The Late Michelangelo", undated (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0348)
  - "Michelangelo and the Medici Chapel", undated
    - Original recording (Box 7, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0363)
    - Access CDs (Box 15, Cd 1991p1, 1991p2)
  - "Michelangelo's Architecture", undated (Box 7, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0361)
    - Original recording (Box 7, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0361)
    - Access CDs (Box 15, Cd 1993p1, 1993p2)
  - "Works by Michelangelo and His Contemporaries in Northern Italy", undated
    - Original recording (Box 7, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0362)
    - Access CDs (Box 15, Cd 1992p1, 1992p2)
- "Have You Read..." with Professor Floyd Zulli, 1966
  - Reel #1 -- Albert Camus' "The Fall", undated; AV2019
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0337)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:10, 4:11)
  - Reel #2 -- "Life and Times of Author Ernest Poole," "Short Stories: Steinbeck", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0336)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:12)
  - Reel #3 -- "Oh Pioneers!: Willa Cather," "Charles Brockden Brown's 'Wieland' Gothic Novel," "The Delight of Classic and Modern Literature: Finley Peter Dunne and His Literary Creation 'Mr. Dooley,'" "The Damnation of Theron Ware by Harold Frederic," "Stories of Stephen Crane", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0335)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:13, 4:14)
  - Reel #4 -- Thomas Paine's "Common Sense"
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0334)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:15, 4:16)
  - "The Stories of Hawthorne," Melville's "Billy Budd", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0333)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:17, 4:18)
- "Philosophical Analysis" with Professor Kai Nielsen, 1966
  - Reel #1 -- "Holbach and the Denial of Human Freedom," "Dostoevsky: Freedom as Irrational Choice," "James, The Dilemma of Determinism," "Determinism, Fatalism and Predestination", September 29 - October 6, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0347)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:30, 3:31)
  - Reel #2 -- "On the Compatibility of Freedom and Determinism," "Crime and Responsibility in a Deterministic World," "Conceptions of Freedom and Responsibility," "Psychoanalysis and Moral Freedom", October 8-15, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0346)
    - Access CDs (Box 12, Cd 3:32, 4:1)
  - Reel #3 -- "Recorded Truth and Validity," "Recorded Truth, Knowledge and Fixation of Belief," "Science and Hypothesis," "Philosophy and Religion: A Preamble", October 18-25, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0345)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:2)
  - Reel #4 -- "St. Anselm and the Ontological Argument," "St. Anselm Revisited: Argument and Counter-Argument," "Aquinas and the Argument from Causality," "Aquinas and the Argument from Contingency", October 27 - November 3, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0344)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:3)
  - Reel #5 -- "Evil and the Argument from Design," "The Appeal to Religious Belief," Discussion on faith and reason, "James: The Will to Believe", November 5-12, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0343)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:4)
  - Reel #6 --"Meaning and Truth: Significance of God Talk," "Religion and Ethics" "Have You Read," "Outsiders and Social Outcasts," "O Piazza Talks," "Religion and Ethics," "Normative Ethics and the Problem of Cultural Relativism," "Utilitarianism", November 15-26, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0342)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:5)
  - Reel #7 -- "Utilitarianism," "Intuitionism in Ethics," "Philosophy of Nietzche," "Philosophy of Sartre and Camus", December 8, 1966
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0341)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:6)
  - Reel #8 -- "Dualism and its Critique of Materialism: Relationship of Mind and Body," "Reductive Materialism and Behaviorism," "Have You Read: O Day del Locust," "Reductive Materialism and Behaviorism," "Morality and Reason", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0340)
    - Access CDs (Box 13, Cd 4:7)
  - Reel #9 -- "Empiricism and the Verification Principle," "Existentialism: Dostoy to Sartre by Walter Kaufman," "Immortality," "Elimination of Metaphysics", undated
    Scope and Contents
    The reel's label is partially illegible.
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0339)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:8)
  - Reel #10 -- "Kant: Metaphysics," "The Challenge of Existentialism," "Metaphysics and the Appeal to Ordinary Logic," "Exist" by W. Kaufman, "The Resurgence of Metaphysics", undated
    - Original recording (Box 6, Quarter inch audio reel 7.3.1.1.0338)
    - Access CD (Box 13, Cd 4:9)
- "RELDot", November 11, 1968; cuid18677 (Box 291, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0464)
- "Theism, Atheism, and Humanism" with Assistant Professor James Carse, November 11, 1968; cuid18678 (Box 292, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0514)
- "Adventures in Mathematical Thinking" with Professor Albert Novikoff, September - October, 1969
  - Episode #9, September 17, 1969 (Box 323, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0406)
  - Episode #37, October 22, 1969 (Box 283, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0452)
- "The Dynamic Earth" with Professor Alistair McCrone, November - December, 1969
  - Video recording, November 6, 1969 (Box 284, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0481)
  - Episode #46, December 22, 1969; cuid18679 (Box 285, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0463)
- "Iranian (Persian) Culture and Civilization" with Assistant Professor Peter Chelkowski, January 28 - May 15, 1970
  - Episode #6, January 28, 1970 (Box 286, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0515)
  - Episode #15, 1970 (Box 287, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0449)
- "The Social Anthropology of Africa" with Professor John Middleton, February, 1970
  - Episode #18, February 16, 1970 (Box 290, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0517)
  - Episode #20, February 16, 1970; cuid18680 (Box 289, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0574)
- "Eisenhower HBC", June 3, 1970 (Box 26, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0451)
- "SOC" -- Episode #39, December 11, 1970; cuid18681 (Box 293, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0462)
- "Early Renaissance Art in Italy" with Assistant Professor Isabelle Hyman, September - December, 1970
  - Episode #2, September 9, 1970 (Box 296, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0162)
  - Episode #43, December 16, 1970 (Box 294, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0460)
- "Fundamental Life Processes" with Associate Professor Fleur L. Strand, March, 1971
  - Episode #30, March 26, 1971 (Box 278, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0418)
    Air date: April 8, 1971
  - Episode #32, March 26, 1971 (Box 277, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0420)
    Air date: April 13, 1971
- "Language: An Introduction to Modern Linguistics" with Associate Professor Lewis Levine, April, 1971
  - Episode #37, April 8, 1971 (Box 279, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0426)
  - Episode #38, April 8, 1971 (Box 280, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0410)
- "Classical Mythology in Literature, Art, and Music" with Professor Philip Mayerson, June - August, 1971
  - "An Introduction to the Course"
    - Original recording
    - Access CD (Box 15, Cd 5:18)
  - Episode #6, June 17, 1971 (Box 281, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0169)
    Air date: October 9, 1971
  - Episode #17, July 8, 1971 (Box 282, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0163)
    Air date: November 4, 1971
  - Video recording, August 12, 1971 (Box 273, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0573)
  - Episode #36, August 26, 1971 (Box 274, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0417)
- "American Urban Politics" with Assistant Professor Charles Billings, September, 1971
  - Episode #3, September 17, 1971 (Box 275, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0485)
  - Episode #5, September 17, 1971 (Box 276, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0396)
- "Death", December 12, 1971 (Box 348, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0445)
- "Earth, Air, Fire, Water and DNA" with Professor Seymour Lewin, December, 1971 - January, 1972
  - Episode #7, December 18, 1971 (Box 270, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0412)
  - Episode #11, January 8, 1972 (Box 271, 2 inch videoreel 7.3.1.1.0456)